# Ao LIU

## Ph.D. in Computer Science

### Summary

Research Machine Learning (Recommendation Systems, Learning to Rank, Algorithm Design, etc.),
Interests Differential Privacy, Computational Social Choice, and Quantum Computation

**Experience** 1+ years of industry experience in personalization, recommendation systems, LLM, theoretical computer science, differential privacy, and adversarial robustness

**Academia** Published 20+ papers, filed 2 patents, and received 250+ citations to date. Reviewed 50+ papers for top AI conferences or journals.

#### Education

01/2018-05/2023 **Ph.D.** in **Computer Science**, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Thesis: Group Decision Makings from Partial Preferences [Link]

08/2015-05/2018 M.Eng. in Material Engineering, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Focus on optics and polymer physics, received Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship

08/2010-05/2014 **B.S.** in **Mathematics and Physics**, Tsinghua University Beijing, China *Minor in Computer Technology*, and *in Academic Talent Program* 

#### Experience

07/2023 – Present Research Software Engineer at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA
Design and Research More Efficient Transformers for Recommendation Systems

05/2022-08/2022 Research Intern at Google Core ML

Mountain View, CA

Project: Unbiased Learning to Rank with a More Accurate Position Bias Estimator

- O Significantly more accurate ( $\sim$ 8%) on predictions v.s. state-of-the-art without any cost
- Proposed a novel probabilistic model to more accurately estimate position bias and designed an unbiased recommendation system based on it.
- Implemented the data pipeline and machine learning algorithm for the proposed unbiased recommendation system. Integrated all into Google codebase. (Python, TensorFlow, C/C++)

05/2019-08/2019 Visiting Scholar at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab

Cambridge, MA

and Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy

08/2018 – 12/2018 • Delivered one academic paper (on top AI journal and conference) and two patents.

- O Significantly more robust ( $\sim$ 12%) and more accurate v.s. state-of-the-art without any cost. Note that we improved two trade-off properties at the same time.
- O Designed the first-ever algorithm with theoretically guaranteed top-k robustness against  $\ell_{\infty}$ -norm attacks, where the theoretical proofs use Rényi differential privacy.
- O Implemented the proposed robust algorithm and tested its robustness, accuracy, and computational efficiency on various tasks, including neural network interpretation, image classification, and objective detection. (PyTorch, TorchRay, TensorFlow, MATLAB)

#### Skills

Implementation Python, C/C++, MATLAB, TensorFlow, PyTorch, TorchRay, LATEX

**Design / Theory** Algorithm design, Time & Sample-complexity analysis, User-modeling, MCMC, Statistics, Privacy analysis, Robustness analysis, Model identifiability, Smoothed analysis

#### Review Services

Journal Information Sciences, TMLR, ACM ToIS, DMLR, Sankhya B

Conference NeurIPS (20, 21, 22, 23, & 24), ICML (22, 23 & 24), ICLR (23 & 24), AAAI (21 & 22), IJCAI-22

|                            | Selected Publications   |
|----------------------------|---|
| TMLR                       | Smoothed Differential Privacy [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yu-Xiang Wang, and Lirong Xia   |
| UAI-23                     | Accelerating Voting by Quantum Computation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qishen Han, Lirong Xia, and Nengkun Yu   |
| AIJ and $AAAI$ -23 (oral)  | Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy [Link] [ArXiv] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaoyu Chen, Sijia Liu, Lirong Xia, and Chuang Gan        |
| AAAI-22                    | The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes [PDF] $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$ and Lirong Xia  |
| UAI-20 (oral)              | How Private Are Commonly-Used Voting Rules? [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yun Lu, Lirong Xia, and Vassilis Zikas  |
| AAAI-19 (oral)             | Near-Neighbor Methods in Random Preference Completion [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qiong Wu, Zhenming Liu, and Lirong Xia  |
| AAAI-19 (oral)             | Learning Plackett-Luce Mixture from Partial Preferences [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Zhibing Zhao, Chao Liao, Pinyan Lu, and Lirong Xia                          |
| ETRA-19 (oral)             | Differential Privacy for Eye-Tracking Data [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Andrew Duchowski, Reynold Bailey, Kenneth Holmqvist, and Eakta Jain          |
| AAAI-23 (oral)             | Differentially Private Condorcet Voting [PDF] Zhechen Li, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, and Hanpin Wang  |
| IJCAI-22 (oral)            |   |
| JAIR and $IJCAI-23$ (oral) | Learning to Design Fair and Private Voting Rules [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia                        |
| ETRA-20 Adjunct            | Let It Snow: Adding Pixel Noise to Protect the Users Identity [Link] Brendan John, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Sanjeev Koppal, and Eakta Jain             |
| •                          | Simulation of Pulse Responses of Lithium Salt-Doped Poly-Ethyleneoxide [Link] <u>Ao Liu</u> , F. Zeng, Y. Hu, S. Lu, W. Dong, X. Li, C. Chang, and D. Guo |
|                            | ► View All Publications at [Personal Website] [Google Scholar]  |
|                            | Patents   |
| US Patent                  | Certifiably Robust Interpretation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Bo Wu, Lirong Xia, Qi Cheng Li, and Chuang Gan   |
| US Patent                  | Interpretation Maps with Guaranteed Robustness [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Abhishek Bhandwaldar, Chuang Gan, Lirong Xia, and Qi Cheng Li             |
|                            | Awards and Teaching   |
| 09/2019 - 05/2022          | RPI-IBM AI Horizon Scholarship  |
| 09/2016 - 05/2017          | RPI Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship [Certificate]   |
| 01/2023 - 05/2023          | Teaching Assistant of CSCI 4150: Introduction to AI   |
| 08/2017 - 12/2017          | Teaching Assistant of MATH 1020: Calculus II  |

04/2021 Guest Lecture at CSCI 4967/6967: Economics and Computation

0